Hello, my name is Romero and today let's
explore how do I like to plan a feature.
We are going to start by making a quick
overview of the project and feature that
we are going to build. After that we are
going to try to identify all the key
responsibilities that are needed to be
covered in order to build this feature.
Once we know that we could try to
structure the work to avoid all the
bottlenecks
and once we have that we are going to go
to the shy part of the thing and we're
going to start to write effective and
amazing ticket to work in a flawless
mode.
After that we're going to try to see how
we could lay all the groundwork in order
to work uh without uh any bottlenecks.
Finally, we are going to see how using
this we can deliver visibility and
incremental features to business.
In this case, we're going to play with a
custom script that I did a few months or
years ago.
Here we will find the repo. You will see
that it cons of three different Python
scripts. It have a pretty basic
configuration runs with name equals main
and it has no test of course because was
uh something that I did just for fun and
have a great lack of separation of
concerns.
Let's review the three main script that
we're going to try to refactor. We are
going to see a monthly habits, a monthly
titles, and a monthly views. you will
see these titles and you may wonder what
are we doing with this kind of a script.
Okay, let me explain you. These three
scripts help me get a lot of information
from the journal that I do each day.
Here I can track all the habits that I'm
following h the titles of the thing that
I write off and I'm able to see this on
the console in a nice and an easy way.
Yeah, it's pretty nerdy but it's what I
like.
So let's try let's start by seeing the
script.
Okay, let's start by seeing the scripts.
Here we have the monthly abbit. This is
the one in charge to get data, process
the data and show the data. Okay. So
here we can we have a class row that is
the one that we use to save the
information. Here we have all the
different tags that I use to find the
information in in the data that I write
all the days. And here are the basic
script. As you will see it's long here
we could start to see some good practice
that I like to implement. Try to not go
uh more than one layer of deepness on
the complexity of the functions and the
functions calling functions just to
avoid uh overhead and difficulty to read
the thing. This is right in a way with
clear variables and a lot of things
trying to see that you could read this
and understand what are we doing without
getting a lot of impact of seeing the
code on trying to get a a lot of
deepness on that. H all clear variable
names and so on.
We have the auxiliary functions here.
And as you may see here,
we have the
script that only does one thing. It take
the month
and generates the data by month. Okay,
this is for the habits. Now we do a
pretty similar thing but with a
different way of processing the data
with all the sheling part the things
that I write day by day. We are
following the same practices but we have
all the things in the same place and
again we have uh the same function
running here. Lastly,
we have this that is the thing that
helps me take the data
modify a little bit the data not much
and show the data uh in different ways
on the console. We have the show all
graph that this helps me show all the
things at the same time from the same
month. I can see the health view line. I
can see the general day line. I can see
the the
habits by month. I can see what the days
I I can see a lot of things. Okay. From
the positive habits and from the
negative habits. And here you could see
that we have fun helper functions that
are here doing all the magic that we
have here. Okay. So let's go back to the
presentation
now.
You may say what are you taking time to
refactor this if this is working. This
is just for the sake of doing this talk
and in order to share the knowledge that
I have and that I like to sh to share.
Um a key thing from this is what do we
want from this now? Because this is
something that I have and it is only
usable for me and it's really tied to
the ways that I do the things. I store
all the information in er tech txt
files.
I use h a single uh way of doing the
things. I use my own erh tax in order to
search the information and I save all
the the data in CSV and that those are
my choices.
But if we want to modify that, if let's
say I don't want to do this uh on my
computer anymore or I want to be able to
travel and do this on my phone and to
generate this data and so on and I want
to connect and I want to take this from
other places and I want to write in
Google Sheets right now or whatever.
Okay,
first thing that we need is scalability.
We need a way
to easily modify this code without
intervening um tossing each other's foot
when we are writing code. Okay. And to
separate the responsibilities, okay, we
need to make this modular. We see that
we are doing in the same script. We are
filling a lot of different uh functions
and that's not good. That's not good
because when we want to test the thing,
we're going to enter in a lot of pain
trying to mock the things being not able
to mock a lot of things on needed to go
pretty deeper in order to mock main
libraries and that's not the best way.
We are going to have tests that test all
of the things and we are not going to be
sure if we're breaking or not things. H
we don't have any tests and that's
something that I would really like to to
add here. And these are the three main
things that we are going to focus on
this talk. Making these three script
something that we could scale, something
that is pretty modular and something
that have comprehensive test.
If you manage to do this in any of the
features that you are doing in your
work, you are going a step forward from
a lot of places that you will be working
or from a lot of things because you will
always have a lot of touch dev and
things that are in any work and that is
normally software development.
So let's continue.
Now that you saw the script, are you
able to identify the responsibilities?
Let's see. First responsibility will be
read the data from the source. We have a
source of data right now. Our txt files
inside my computer, but this could be a
Google drive, an S3 bucket, could be
whatever we need to read to get data
from a source. This could be from an API
that I want to expose.
Never. I'm going to never do that, but
it could be. Okay, the main
responsibility is to get the data.
After getting the data, we need to
process and manipulate the data. Okay,
this is another completely different
responsibility. Once we get the data,
doesn't matter where the data cames, we
need to be able to process that data.
This is a key responsibility and it's a
pretty independent thing that the script
need to do.
After that we are going to need to store
the data. Right now we are storing in a
different format
but in the same place. Tomorrow we will
say maybe I can store this in
a SQL database in a non-SQL database. I
want to store this uh in an S3 bucket. I
want to store this in a Google drive
wherever. This is different from getting
the data is this is storing the data.
And finally we want to display the data
that we have. Okay.
The thing that for sure will stay stay
the same will be the processing and the
manipulation of the data. But that's the
key part and is the one that most test
will need. Okay. But
reading the data from anywhere could
change and this is something that we
need to change and be able to scale to
to take out to take put to put in and to
be able to always
give data doesn't matter how. So that's
modularity. We could change this have a
a a script that brings data from a a
computer one that does that from a
Google drive that well but and if I
provide you with the basis script you
will be able to start changing the the
things in order to accommodate to your
specific needs okay processing the the
data okay you will need to follow some
things and will not change a lot but
it's okay but it's a separate process
and it's important one. Storing the data
is the same thing. We need the
modularity of being able to say, hey, I
want to change this from saving the data
here to here. And that will have their
own language, their own way of doing
things, their way to of testing things,
their own caveats. Okay. And finally,
displaying the data is exactly the same.
You will need you will talk about using
different libraries, different things.
So this is the modularity that we need
and this is the scalability that we need
and that thinking the things in this way
will provide you easier ways to change
things al as long as you will need in
the process. Okay.
Now let's continue.
Let's start thinking how we can
structure the work in order to avoid the
bottlenecks. We're going to start by
making a client class. The client class
will be the class that will go get that
get the data whatever the class one to
the place that the class one whatever
and will return a Python object in order
to be used
by the data processing class that is the
next class that we are going to build.
We are going to need a data processing
class. This data processing class will
be in charge of creating the different h
structures of data that we need or
extract all the data that we need and
return a Python object that will be easy
to save on whatever place we want. Okay.
But we need to process the data and
return the different pieces. Right now
we have we know that we have h data for
the monthly titles. We have data for the
monthly habit view. Okay. So we have two
different kind of data that we need to
process and to extract from the files.
After that we are going to use the
repository class to save the data. This
class is going to have the only
responsibility of saving the data. Today
it's always going to save the data that
is being provided by the data processor.
Okay, the same data. But today it's
going to save it in in a CSV file.
Tomorrow could save it in JSON. H the
day after could be saved on a Google
Drive. The day after could be saved on a
a SQL uh SQL database. Okay? Doesn't
matter. This class is the one that will
hold all the logic that will take to
interact with the source place that we
are going to store the data.
After that we are going to make a class
that only talks about graphic things. In
this case will be a graphic console uh
class data. Huh a typo. Okay.
This will be a a graphic console. So we
are going to talk about printing things
but we could say hey I want to this
using mattplot lib or seaborn or I want
to do this by using a streaml and
putting this in a front end or whatever
doesn't matter you will need to take
some data and after that show that data
and finally and the most important one
and this is the most that the one that I
most like is the service layer. The
service layer is the one that rule them
all. Is the one that knows how to change
the pieces, how to tie all the things
and it's where all the logic will be
spelled. Okay, we will have single uh
functions in one of these class classes
that give things and the service is the
one that is going to say hey I'm going
to provide this service this h creation
of data or this showing this data and in
order to do that I'm going to call the
client and going to say hey client
please give me this data data processor
please process this d this data in this
way repository save this here and then I
I could say to the CR cons graphic hey
give me this data from here and let me
uh show this in this way whatever all
the logic will be there and these are
going to be all the functions that are
going to be used by us the end users
okay
good
so let's see some keys and let me show
you a brief uh example of what we are
going to end up with so We need to
display the data. We need to identify
all the dependencies.
And let me show you what will be
example. This is the road map that I
built using uh the GitHub road map. SA
has way more uh nice features and you
could do the connection between all the
tickets.
But here you will be able to see that
this project took 36 tickets. Okay, 36
tickets
in order to build the whole things from
the base to the finish line.
Here we can see that we make a milestone
that is uh the to set up the project.
You can see that we separate all the
ticket between the client, the data
processor, the repository, the console
graphic, the service. We have a cl a cle
the client and we start being able to
build all the things.
After this we are going to go more deep
and more deep into these ones. If you
want maybe we could see
how a my stone looks like we have the
tickets here.
Let's see one example ticket.
You could see here that you can see the
dependencies. you have a lot of info but
I'm spoiling things so we are going to
go back and we are going to continue
with the presentation but this is just
to show you a little bit of how this
looks like okay let's go back
okay
we see another typo here and I need to
do a lot of things in order to change
this so I'm not going to do it so now
we're going to start seeing how we can
write effective tickets and a key part
from this for me is doing a concise but
yet informative descriptions. Okay, we
don't want endless paragraph of
information but we want to understand a
little bit what we are doing, why we are
doing that. Okay,
we need clear acceptance criteria. We
need acceptance criteria that help us
understand how we are going to test the
things, how we are going to be sure that
this is working as expected. These kind
of tickets needs to be built alongside
the PMS or the POS or however they are
calling it in your company but we need
to try to understand that we are doing
the things as we expect
and this is a part that I I really like
and it's add relevant relevant
additional information. What's that?
It's the place that we are going to be
working on. Imagine that you are on a
team with more than five GitHub
repositories or five microservices
and you are starting to work there. You
will need a lot of this information.
Imagine that you're working from the
last two years, three years and that you
were focused on two of those
microservices when you need to jump to
the other microservices. You will need
this information that will help you what
where is the place that uh you need to
work. If you have any business
information,
if you have any system design erh
information will be a pretty good place
to put it here. If you have a similar
implementation of something like that,
that would be a good place to put that
here. Um
finally and this is the thing that for
me is most important in order to build
visibility and to the business and to
the developers is the explicit
dependencies between the ticket. You
need to know who is blocking you, who is
not blocking you, what is blocking you
more than who.
Okay, let's start seeing some tickets
and talk a little bit about them.
This will be a ticket to implement the
base class. Okay, in order to do this
because this was our factor and I knew
what are the things that we are going to
need from this specific class. I say hey
what if we have a ticket that create the
base class create the base configuration
from the for this and create all the
different functions that we are going to
expose from this class
with a not implemented error. So after
that each member of the team could enter
and start working on those functions
within having a merge conflicts and so
on. So this is how we structure this
ticket and all the tickets here. So the
description this class is responsible
for receiving data from the showner.
Okay. Uh it should access a
configurative road on the machine h
using this script.
um this variable need to be configurable
blah blah blah blah blah. Here we are
explaining what do we need and why do we
need we need it acceptant criteria. We
need a local client class. We need a
configurable shal deer. Okay, we need
all this function with a not implemented
error and this one with h imple
implemented and tested. Okay, this is
clear. There is no way to to fail if you
have this kind of abset criteria. Sorry
that I'm being like this, but I'm a
little bit passionate when I'm talk. Uh,
and here what do you have? You have all
the information and leaks. You have a
getway documentation from another talk
that I did. You have all the example
data. This is this is amazing. And you
have the example screen. Uh, and
finally, we have the dependencies. Okay,
let's go back to the presentation.
Okay, I think a well doumented ticket
was the one that we see saw before. And
here is one more ticket with some
examples because we are talking about a
graphic things and for you to see what
we want to show. This is an example.
Here we have the criteria and here you
can see what we need to show what is
being need to show. So you will be able
to have a clear view of what we need to
develop in this case in the case in most
of the cases this will be a Figma thing
if you have front end or things like
that. Okay. And again info and links we
have the dependencies and we have all
the acceptant criteria and the
description.
Good. With this we have a quick
overview. This is this we could go
deeper and deeper into this but for me
it's not going to make sense right now.
It's for you to start exploring with
your team and trying to understand what
are the things that you need in a
ticket. What are the things that let you
get unblocked easily?
And as you also are going to see here,
let's go back here
and let's go to the projects.
Here we have 37 tickets. 36 tickets.
Okay,
this is not a lot of work. This is
something that we could do
not in a week, not in a sprint, but we
could really work on this. But the key
factor is creating small ticket, small
functions in each function here has
their own ticket. It's not create the
client and build all the functionality
into the client. No, let's start by
doing this small and this is done to
understand is that it's done by
understanding the different
responsibilities and how we could tie
them in order to see hey if I build this
small part of the client and if I build
this small part from the data processor
and if I build this small part from the
repository and if I build this small
part from the console graphic blah blah
blah blah class I just forgot the if
I could give a small feature. Okay, so
we are doing small parts for each part
of the work. So we have
instant gratification something that we
all need. Okay, we have small things we
are going to fight one issue at a time
and I'm not talking about issues of
github issues. I'm talking about things
that we need to solve one at a time, one
small part. If we are going if we try to
fight with all at the same time we are
going to get get overloaded we are going
to get burned out and that's not
something that we want. So try to be
smart try to break the work in the
smaller part uh that you can and then do
a lot of tickets feel free to do a
dollars ticket a lot of small tickets.
Uh it's not bad. I really like to work
like that.
Now let's continue.
Okay, we're going to see the different M
minds that I create. We get a a glance
of that earlier. We are going to see why
did I choose to uh implement all the
base classes.
We are going to see all the test data
that I create and prepare for this to be
built. And well, as you saw earlier, we
have pretty well doumented tickets.
Okay. So let's start by the milestones
that I create.
Whoop.
As you may see here,
we have the setup the setup of the
project
as the first milestone. This milestone
consist in creating the structure of the
project. This will be using a template
if you have a template in your company.
Modifying the things act sample fields
to use. This is part of the setup. Okay,
we need to add all the examples or all
the testing data in this case that we
have that this is part a key part of
building the project in order to let the
team work afterward without any
problems. And after that, I choose the
base tickets that I need to implement in
each class in order to allow the team to
go full H mode after that. So as you may
see I create the base class from the
console graphic tool. I create the base
class with one uh function implemented
from the data processor. I create the
service the clay the data processor the
repository and the client. Okay. Uh yes.
Good. Now let's see the other
milestones. What do I have here? We have
the client with all the functions as you
see. So here I implement this tree as
you see I create I implement this tree
that are independent. I want to get the
field hath by month. I want to get the
monthly habits by month
and I have these two that I don't need
to do it right now but I can do it okay
later in an in another state. Now
same thing with the data processor.
I need to process the that data into two
different ways and here are the
functions in order to do that. Pretty
easy, pretty well documented with all
the information, with all the links,
with the dependencies.
Anyone can come here and start working
in whatever they want.
Here we have the repository.
I have all the things implemented here.
We have the console graphic. Same thing.
All the functions that are implemented
that need to be used. You have here all
the things separated and it's easy to
understand and you are not going to toss
in anyone's else foot. And I made this
project for the Py Camp of 2025 with the
idea that I could have people just
jumping here saying, "Hey, I want to try
to show things on the console. Hey, here
you have a thing that you can do and you
are not being blocked by any other part
of the um of the workflow. I want to
know how to
process some data. I want to play with
that. Here you have I want to get some I
will be able to provide to the people in
the py camp tools to play with whatever
they want without being blocked by
anyone else.
Okay, let's go back.
Let's take a look to the data to the
base data that we have here. So,
this is
all the data that you will have. Okay,
you will need to process this data.
And if you see here, I create a bunch of
dummy data using a script h made by
the artificial intelligence that really
helped me build some dummy data
and you will have all the things that
you need to process. So it will be easy
for you to test to play to understand.
Okay. So here we could see a lot of
tests that are being done using the data
that we have here that it's a that some
dummy data. Okay. So we can check the
things we can see that we are showing
the things as we want here using this uh
this kind of code that seems pretty
crazy but it's showing what we really
want. And in this way we could play. I
have a lot of test and do things. And I
have os here that really help me and
enjoy being able to show all this data
and commit some things to here. So that
was pretty nice.
Okay. Well doumented tickets. Again we
saw that earlier. Let's take some time
to talk about testing. Okay.
What's the difference between the unit
test and the integration test?
In this case, we will have mostly unit
test because we are not using thirdarty
services like for example a Google drive
client or a MySQL client or whatever or
a MySQL repository. We are not doing a
lot of those things. So we can we don't
need to mock things in order to do what
we need. But basically the unit test
will be the ones that try to do the
things in the smaller way possible.
Okay, we are going to test each
function. If you enter here, you're
going to see test for each function as
and helper functions that we have on the
code. We're going to test each one of
them in order to ensure ensure that they
are doing what we really need that what
we really want. Okay. And this is also a
great documentation. And then when we
come to the integration test in the case
on of a more corporate uh product you
will see that you will have all the
things uh with the database for example
with a dummy database not a real
database but a dummy database with a
docker compose but same database engine
all the things and you will test all the
things there to see that they are
working as they work. We should not h
abuse the mocking of the things. It's
good to be able to mock some things
sometimes, but it's important also to
understand how they all work together.
And in the integration test, you will
see for example all the things from the
service. The service that is the one
that integrates all the things will be
the one that integrate the things and
you will have the whole flow there.
Okay. So that's uh something that I want
to clarify that for me it's pretty
important.
Also you can do contract test for
example those are another kind of test
that you can do when you are using
thirdarty services you are depending on
an API and you want to check that it's
returning always the data that you
expect. You make a call you check that
you have the data and that's it. That's
a contract test. You can do end to end
test. You can do API test as we call uh
going uh with and in a stationing or or
latest. You can do test hitting the APIs
from the first part and going through
all the process in order to understand
the things are working.
The minimum things that you should have
are unit test and integration test on
the repo with as much coverage as you
can.
This is a part that the PMS were waiting
for. Delivering visibility and
incremental features to the business.
What an amazing group of words that you
could give to your PMs.
Sorry, it's funny for me, but it's the
reality. And it's not not only for the
PMs, it's also for the dev team. It's
pretty important for the team to be able
to have all these things to have
visibility to understand what is
blocking them what is not what h could
help us go and advance to deliver some
things and could come back uh to
continue doing other things. A small
ticket will let them work in a smoother
way. So this is for all but usually
sounds more like is for the business
people.
So let's go.
Here you saw the road map the road map
earlier. Okay let's go back and here you
will see how all the work is splitted.
Sadly this tool doesn't let me have the
connections between the tickets. Okay.
But when you are working with tools like
Shira or with other tools that let you
have the dependencies connected, you
will see lines with these tickets and
you will be easily able to understand
what are the different flows that you
need that you can implement at the same
time because by doing the dependencies
you could go here and say hey here all
of these depend on this. Okay, once I
get rid of these three tickets, I can
can put as many people as ticket as I
have to rush this part in one sprint and
get rid of that and continue with the
next part and so on and so on and so on.
And again having these tools helps you
planify the work, helps you think and
say, "Hey, right now we can put only two
people to work in this sprint on this
feature because we have blocking parts
that doesn't allow us to put more than
two people. in next sprint maybe we can
put five people or six people and
instead of having people waiting in into
other people that it's blocking them we
could put them do another things you can
go shop and see hey I can do this other
ticket I can work in this other thing
that I have interest on hey I want to
switch from this feature to the other
you can do things once you have the
vision and and you have a clear path to
follow it's going to be easier for you
for the team from the business and you
could give estimated dates here you
could put all the things here and lay
out all the dependencies and after that
you could say for example I will say
that this will take like at least four
sprints let's say and you can negotiate
with business say hey this ideally will
take four sprints
let's say that we're going to that is
going to take five and a half to have
some backup there in order that
something happened and maybe you will
need that maybe not and you will
delivering on time you will give him
visibility and each time that you have a
problem you could come and say hey man
this happened here we find this bag we
create the ticket it's here this delays
the work in this way and you will be
able to have good talks and move forward
and all be happier than trying to figure
it out how is the thing going why it's
not going as we expected and so
For me, these kind of graphic tools
really helps me have good conversations
h and move forward and create features
in a better way.
So
that's it for today. I really thank you
spending time to hear me and hear about
what I have to say.
If you have any feedback, just let me
know in the comments. DM me on linkadin.
I'm pretty open uh to talk to learn
more. H this is what works for me and
for the teams that I've been working on
from the last for the last years. H and
it's something that is pretty proof on
the experience.
But I'm sure it's not the best way. It's
not the most amazing way. It's a way
that works for me. And if you have
something better, please let me know so
I can learn and improve. Thanks.